Thank you, everybody, for joining us
today to go through this walkthrough
of the Foundry platform.
There's a lot to cover, so it'll be
a bit of a whirlwind tour.
I won't be able to get to
everything, but I'll try to give you
a representative cross sample of
kind of the key parts of the
platform.
Foundry behind the scenes is 100+
different microservices kind
of surfaced up as kind of two dozen
different out-of-the-box user facing
applications, actually a bit more.
In addition to applications that you
can also build. And these
applications stretch across
effectively every persona in
the modern enterprise.
So we'll try to take a tour through
kind of some of those key personas
and call out what kind of tools or
services are used at every step
along the journey.
You know, we can think about the
functionality and foundry kind of in
three main parts.
So there is the data and ontology
piece. So how are we connecting to
different data sources, data lakes,
data warehouses and bringing that
data together into a semantic
foundation that can then be used by
the entire organization.
We call this an ontology.
So we'll talk about the journey of
how we connect into different data
sources, refine them, build
out data integrations with
health checks, security, and kind of
build out this ontology as
sort of a starting place
will then want to bring in kind of
data science and modeling into that
same foundation.
So this is sort of the sphere of
digital twin and modeling.
So how do we think about leveraging
business logic, data science,
ML, LP models
within the same foundation that
we've built on the data side?
So kind of trying to fuze data
and models together into a common
foundation through this ontology.
And then kind of finally, we'll talk
about how the combination of data
and models comes together
for different types of end users.
So, you know, these are everyday
users doing core operational
functions in the organization,
and this is 70 to 80 percent
of users of Foundry in most contexts
are sort of quote unquote
non-technical users trying to
make use of the fruits of all that
labor towards real operational
workflows and different
applications that are kind of
existential to the business.
So let's start at the
top with data and ontology.
So what I want to do is first go
into a first application
here, which is called Monocle, which
is sort of our data lineage graph
for the story of kind of how the
data comes together into an
ontology.
So here you'll see this is a pretty
notional example.
So it's a little bit simplified a
supply chain ontology, right, which
is showing me kind of the
different concepts I'm going to work
with in my supply chain demo.
So I've put together common
concepts, right? Like a supplier, an
alert, a distribution center,
plants, materials, et cetera.
And each of these also have each
of these objects have links between
them. We'll go into how each of
these objects also has actions
associated with them.
But the idea is, is that if we look
at kind of any one of these objects,
so we're going to go into the plant
to begin with here to start.
Each of these is the culmination of
many different steps of data
integration.
So if we zoom out here, what we see
kind of in this spiderweb diagram
is the story of how we integrated
different data sources to build this
plant object to start with on the
right hand side.
So reading this from left to right,
what we see here is we're actually
pulling in kind of a couple
different data sources.
Typically, these diagrams are much,
much larger, much, much more
complex. But this is just a starting
example of us connecting to.
You'll see on the left hand side
and SAP system as an example
of one business system,
Treasury.gov, which is an example
of an open API-driven source
for connecting to.
And then I have a time series source
here too, which is a synthetic
sensor that I've set up just sort of
in my environment to work with.
And the idea is that every one of
these steps, every one of these sort
of rectangles or nodes you see in
the graph is one step closer
to refining, cleaning, joining,
applying business logic to that data
to get us to that semantic
representation.
So for instance, if I kind of take a
look at one of these datasets, I can
always sort of pop up and say, OK,
what does this data actually look
like? So let's take a look at the
PySpark code here that
actually shows us how we're actually
applying logic at this step in the
pipeline.
If I select a different node, I can
go and take a look at the history
tab, and I can see that we have full
data versioning for every
version of the data that's updated
in this particular part of the
pipeline. And this is huge because
I can go back and take a look and
say, "OK, who actually updated
this particular routine or this
particular schedule of this data
build?
What was the actual result for this
version of the data versus the
current version of the data?
And how can you actually roll
forward and backwards through
different versions of the data with
the code and the metadata at each
point in time?".
So it's a powerful ability for me to
not only look at data pipelines as
they exist today, but also be able
to look at historically how they
might have changed over time.
There's a few other things I want to
make sure that we call out here kind
of in this part of the
Foundry platform.
So kind of the build system for data
or the data ops part of things.
The first is, you see kind of these
lines connecting all these different
nodes together, and this is
indication of of lineage
and. Lineage is actually a concept
that is intertwined with security
in the Foundry platform.
So we think about how we're securing
data and how that security will flow
into the ontology and into
workflows. Beyond that, let's
actually change the view here for a
second to take a look.
So we're going to change here to the
permissions view and you'll see here
that it's now showing me dynamically
what my perms---, what my
permissions are across this entire
pipeline.
So you'll see it's blue, I have
access to everything here because
I'm sort of the administrator here
of this environment.
But what's actually happening is
we're assigning permissions
to the data sources.
So the SAP system, Treasury.gov,
et cetera.
Basically, the role based access
permissions that might be coming in
from an active directory system or
some sort of other authorization
scheme that an organization has,
and we're then propagating those
controls forward.
So that means that every child
will inherit the union of all the
permissions of its parents
to make that a little bit less
esoteric, let's use another example.
If I change this permissions view,
which I can do as an admin, to my
colleague Jason Richardson,
we'll see that Jason doesn't have
access to most things here.
And that's because he didn't have
access to anything except for the
Treasury.gov source.
And so when the permissions flow,
he's going to lose access the moment
we start to blend that source with
other sources.
You'll notice he actually has one
sort of exceptional piece of access
here where he should have known that
he would have not had access
originally, which is on this OFAC
clean data set because we actually
chose to situationally expand
his permissions in this case,
but not allow that to sort of
propagate forward to any other
pieces of the pipeline.
The point here is is that we can mix
and match very different types of
security models to get very
granular, robust results
so we can intermingle role based
access controls, classification
based access controls and purpose
based access controls all here.
So we can have very fine grained
control over who is doing what,
with different personas, different
parts of the organization through
Foundry.
And this was very much built from
our own experience in the field as
Palantir engineers, where if you
thought about just doing security
based off of the location of data
and some sort of file system or some
sort of bucket location, it became
really hard to actually make sure
that security was robust as that
organization organically started to
pull that data into other places.
So data and security
kind of flow together with lineage,
and it's immutable as you work
throughout the rest, throughout the
entire platform or interact through
the APIs.
So that's sort of the first
thing to call out here is security
is sort of baked right in as part of
the metadata in Foundry.
The second piece I want to call out
here as we kind of work through
things is "OK, so I build out these
pipelines that get to be quite
robust to refreshing all the time.
How do I keep these things healthy?"
And so if I change this to now
a data health view, what we're going
to see here is this is a view into
the parts of the pipeline that I've
instrumented with data quality
checks, and I can always kind of pop
this open at the bottom to say,
let's take a look at the checks that
we have across this part of this
pipeline.
So I'm going to take a look here
at one of these nodes, and we
can take a look and say, let's add a
data health check here.
This is going to pull up a list of
out-of-the-box health checks that we
can sort of assign to different
points in our pipelines.
So is this data updating on time?
Is it refreshing on the schedule
that I expected? Are the files
the size that I expect?
And are we seeing the cardinality
of different data columns with the
statistical results that we expect?
All of these things can be
quantified here through
point-and-click, but can also be set
through code as well.
So we'll go in in a second on how we
actually author these
transformations,
but the data health
component is key to keeping
these pipelines healthy as they're
sort of refreshing all the time.
And so having these checks right
here saves you having to go to a
different platform to kind of see
what's going on there before you
kind of come back to this platform
here.
All right.
So let's now switch back
to our sort of, our default
view, and let's take a look at more
detail on what's actually going on
in these individual steps.
So I'm going to open up one of these
sort of, these the steps
of logic here, and we're going to go
in and take a look at the repository
and how this particular result was
built.
So this is going to launch me into
another application in Foundry
called Authoring, which is an
IDE or an integrated development
environment where I can see here
how I can actually make changes to
this part of this pipeline with kind
of full change management built in.
So the key thing here is that you'll
see, like we saw in Monocle,
the previous application, there's
sort of this branch icon here at the
top. And what this allows us to
do is treat data
the way that we treat code.
And so instead of making changes on
the master branch and trying to then
propagate my changes through which
could cause all sorts of downstream
issues of not careful, what
we've actually done is virtualized
the entire change management process
that would normally involve going to
a UAT environment, but have done it
directly here in one instance,
a foundry using logical isolation
in a cloud-native paradigm.
So what I can do if I want to make
changes here is I actually open
up a branched version of this
part of the pipeline.
And then when I've made my changes
on that branch, I then create
a pull request to actually
merge my changes back into
the master branch.
So if we go into some of the old
pull requests, take a look at what
these proposed changes look like, we
can actually see line-by-line kind
of what those changes were.
And we can also get an impact
analysis of, if we were to merge
this into master, what would be
affected? And because security again
gets blended through different
parent permissions and different
role paradigms, what security
changes would actually occur as
well? And you'd see we didn't
actually see any in this particular
case.
This is a huge difference from the
normal process of saying, OK, if I
wanted to make changes, I'd have to
clone all my pipelines and data over
to a UAT environment, separate
environment, make some changes
and then hopefully say a prayer
and then port them back to master
and hope that everything just sort
of works. Here, we can
actually do that entire process
with total logical isolation, total
sandboxing, here.
We can iterate on these branched
versions of the data and actually
use different kind of analytics
tools and visualization tools with
that branch data that we'll look at
later and then we can choose to
come back and then merge that into
master.
And the most powerful thing about
this is everything is sort of
git-based in terms of semantics.
You'll see here the clone icon at
the top, which means if we ever want
to go back to a prior version of
master or any of the other branches,
we have a full commit log as well.
So we're never, sort of, out
of luck if we merged something in
that we realized later has to
actually be undone.
We can always just move back like
we can in Git with code to a
previous form of the data.
And so being able to treat data like
code, having tje health checks,
having the integrated security, we
think gives you the build system to
be able to go really fast when it
comes to assembling and growing
these data pipelines organically,
which is always the case, right?
These never sort of, sort of,
waterfall method to building these
things upfront that never changes.
It's always a constant sort of state
of iteration and being able to try
to keep up with the latest demands.
I want to show you guys one more
thing before we go into the ontology
and kind of bump things up a level.
We've talked a lot about being able
to author kind of data pipelines
here the way that you can actually
author pipelines and Foundry
is, you know, by default, we
actually offer two out -of-the-box
compute engines that are
auto-scaling.
So this is Flink.
We're running on Kubernetes for
streaming computation and spark
running on Kubernetes for batch
computation.
And so you can do any
you can basically use any languages
that have bindings to those two
runtimes.
And so if we go back to kind of our
repository here, we'll see where
we're using PySpark, we can
use Spark sequel, we can use Java,
we can use Scala.
We even have bindings for Groovy.
And so we adhere to open standards
all the way through when it comes to
code authoring and critically when
it comes to data formats as well.
So if you ever want to look at
what's happening with kind of the
resulting data in any step
of any sort of transformation in
Foundry, if we kind of look
at what's happening here in the
preview or we go to the History tab
here, we'll take a look and we can
see that any of the data
here is effectively
just data that's in parquet or
in Avro or in sort of any open
format that I'd expect.
So I can always interoperate easily
with any of the data here in
Foundry.
And critically, even though we're
using Spark and Flink as our
runtimes, if we take a peek
at what's actually happening under
the hood with Foundry's build
service, we'll see it's just calling
those two runtimes because we've
registered them with Foundry.
And so if you have a high
performance computing environment or
you have something that's an
external compute engine like you're
using something like another Spark
environment or a proprietary
runtime, we can register that
runtime with Foundry as an external
build worker.
And when we refresh these pipelines,
you do the orchestrations, Foundry
will know at certain steps to go and
federate that computation to that
build worker, which allows
you again to have a totally
extensible compute framework here
with what we think is great starting
defaults. But you're never sort of
locked in to just using the compute
that we provide as part of Foundry.
All right.
So one more thing to show you guys
and then let's bump it up a level.
So we talked about being able to
compute these pipelines and
author them manually.
What about data systems that we've
seen over and over again, like the
SAP's and the other ERPs of the
world or the CRMs?
So what we try to do there
is try to say, can we actually
implement what we think of as
software-defined data integrations
where you don't have to manually
redo the kind of cleaning
and transforming work that we
think is actually quite standardized
and possible through kind of
ML-assisted techniques?
So what I'm going to do is actually
open up the kind of data source
for this SAP instance we're
connected to internally.
And we're going to take a look here
at kind of how this looks.
So this is the SAP explorer
that we have kind of as a kind of a
rich connection interface here.
And you'll see it's showing me kind
of all the modules in my ERP estate
like my MM, my data dictionaries.
And it's also even pre-populating
some workflows I might want to do
typically that are common for SAP.
And the power here is that instead
of having to think about browsing
through all the individual tables
myself, we have a
native connector connecting at the
application layer, which is called
NetWeaver, and we're actually
dynamically pulling out all the rich
metadata that actually tells us
much more than just the raw table
information in SAP.
Like we're able to see all the
German acronyms auto-translated
for me. We're able to see kind of
the foreign keys, the relationships,
and the idea here is that we can
kind of derive out that federated
lineage and then auto build
pipelines and even starting objects
in a matter of hours, as opposed
to weeks or months of manually
recreating SAP transformations
on the Foundry side.
And this applies critically not just
to standard modules like MM
or SD or DD, but also
Z tables that you might have
customized. Because we're not just
doing static mapping, we're doing a
dynamic inference of the metadata
through NetWeaver.
And so if you have a very custom SAP
estate or CRM estate and many people
do, it's very simple to
install the SAP connector, which
is, you know, certified native,
and be able to browse around
and then kind of in a shopping cart
like experience, pull in the data
that's of interest to you into
a set of pipelines in Foundry that
you then start to work with.
And actually, that was how we
created these green pipelines here
that we saw before, and we saw
what was actually produced was
PySpark.
So even if it gives us a starting
set of pipelines, we can always
choose to expand that.
We're never sort of given some sort
of black box output that we can't
change.
And so that's an example of,
for more common systems, the
CRMs, the ERPs, the others of
the world, how we're trying to
invest in speed, time
to value speed for our customers
to say "we don't want you to have to
redo all those integrations if it's
not required."
All right.
So we've talked a lot about, in this
first mile, kind of getting data
into the ontology.
Now let's actually talk about the
ontology itself and a little bit
more depth.
So I'm going to go now into one
of these objects and kind of pop the
hood on what's actually happening
here. So to do that, I'm going to
jump into our ontology management
application.
And this is a view that a data
governance kind of team
member or a part of the business
working with it might start to get
involved. Or they might say, "OK,
we've done all the integration work
now let's decide how we're going to
actually make this appear to end
users," right?
So everything from this plant object
we've been working with, is it a
normally visible object?
Is it hidden? Is it prominent?
Is it something we're experimenting
on? Or is it actually an active
object that people should be using
daily for different workflows?
Literally, how are we mapping in
every element from those kind of
golden kind of datasets we
produced into object
form? So things like geospatial
properties, how are those coming in?
What is the API name for these
different properties and the actual
IDs as well?
Because we're gonna want to use this
with all of our different tools kind
of in lots of different kind of
architectures,
and you'll see we have all this
information kind of rolled up here,
right? Including kind of the link
types, usage information
and on the sidebar here, we even
have ways to go in and say, I want
to apply additional security
here, restricted views.
I can do that here as well.
I can also prime these objects
for different types of workflows.
So it might be the case that this
plan objects going to be be
primarily doing simulation based
workflows or geospatial workflows.
And what we can do here is sort of
preset some metadata which
you can always manually set
ourselves that will just get us
again time to value faster.
Let's get these objects up and
running so we can now start to work
with them.
And the idea is you do a little bit
of configuration work here, which
again can be templatized to a large
degree, and business users can then
dive in and immediately start to
make use of this data in a host of
different out-of-the-box
applications in Foundry.
So let's take a look at some of
those applications that kind of come
to life for a business user, for
somebody who's non-technical, who
probably isn't starting their
journey in Foundry in the data
lineage application, in the coding
environments or kind of in the
ontology management interface,
either. They're probably starting in
an application like Object Explorer,
which is a kind of point-and-click
way to be able to browse around
different information in the
ontology and sort of
feel very familiar to folks who are
kind of searching for information
or kind of using kind of different
sort of web applications day in and
day out.
So you'll see here that
I have a lot of different objects
here that are surface to me in
Object Explorer.
I've got my aircraft, my delays, my
flights, from my aviation demo.
I've got some marketing objects here
called interactions campaigns,
offers, things like that, and
to search for something, it's as
simple as searching for a type of
object I'm looking for or any
individual object property.
So in this case, I want to look at
those plants we saw before, and
what this will do is actually launch
me into an investigation or
exploration that's been kind of
pre-configured for me
to be able to start to explore this
data.
So this is it's a very simple sort
of set of visualizations here,
right? It's showing me kind of where
the where the plants are geospatial
based on that geo data that we
affixed.
It's showing me some roll-up
statistics like 30 days of
inventory, production capacity,
things like that.
And if I want to go into a 360-view
and one of these plants, I have a
list here to be able to start to
kind of dive in and take a look at
some of this information at kind of
a higher level.
And the idea here is that, you know,
it's intended to feel familiar again
to folks who have worked with kind
of business intelligence or
visualization software and
just roll up all that information
that's coming from all those
different data sources in a single
view. Right. So I can see
information about, like again, the
geospatial information.
It's address some unstructured
data, like a schematic, maybe some
risk factors or material information
coming in from the ERP and EMS
systems and even things like
timelines as well here.
And these, like 360 views, can look
very custom and very different,
depending on the user type or the
business unit.
And you might imagine that you know
there are certain users that want to
see IoT information or video
information embedded here and others
that want to see financial
information or kind of more kind of
CFO style of use.
And so you can have different lenses
or different kind of views assembled
on the same types of objects here
and the power of object you splurge
that allows people to traverse the
different objects in a completely
security compliant way
and at a scale which you could have
millions or billions of different
objects here where we're actually
allowing people to kind of traverse
in a way that that makes sense and
isn't overwhelming.
Or isn't too granular or unfamiliar
for folks who are familiar with kind
of -- more business centric tooling.
So this is just one view into the
data, though, I think it's important
to realize that so you know, it's
point and click, it's kind of based
off of the object's in
this paradigm.
But if I'm somebody who is a more
technical user like an engineer
or somebody who's an analyst that
maybe is used to working with series
data, I might use a sibling
application of object explorer,
which is called Quiver. And Quiver
here actually allows me to look at
charting information on time
dependent data coming in.
So this is going to be streaming
data coming in in real time
in an oil and gas context or in
utilities context.
And as a user who might be using an
application like this, I'm probably
thinking in terms of not just
point-and-click, but in terms of
formulas and integrals
and interpolation and scatter
plots. And I can actually derive
new data here.
Just through point-and-click.
So I can say, you know, give me the
summation of these two series,
produce another series.
Let me actually look at the
ongoing differential between these
two pressures, and let's produce
another pressure.
I can even do things that are more
sophisticated, like let me do a
search across these series for any
time the difference in these values
is beyond a certain threshold.
Or let me actually do a
point-and-click training of a first
approximation machine learning
model. So I actually want to build a
classifier, and maybe
I kind of tinker with that here as
somebody who is an engineer.
And then I want to be able to then
collaborate with somebody who's a
data scientist on my team.
And so I can export kind of my first
approximation to Python
code, kind of with full library
semantics for interacting with this
time series data in Python as well.
And again, the power here is it
looks pretty technical, looks pretty
custom, but at the end of the day,
I'm just interacting with those
objects in my ontology like we saw
before, so I can just kind of browse
for more objects and plop them onto
these plots to be able to use them.
So another view into that
ontology that we built that
can be serviced by another type
of user.
If I think geospatial, let's say
not just IoT centric or maybe object
centric, I might want to use
an application like the Foundry map,
where I'm looking at kind of all my
plants and distribution centers
kind of here, and I can kind of
toggle layers on and off as I
expect.
And I might want to say, you know,
let's take a look at, you know, for
this particular distribution center,
show me kind of
in a graph-oriented manner, all the
customers connected to this
distribution center, and it's going
to visualize that here and allow me
to kind of explore, you
know, the different flows or kind of
supply or logistics information that
might pertain to the dependencies
between different objects.
And so this is another common view,
again, looking at the same ontology
just through a different lens.
And so this hopefully gives you an
idea of if you do that work of kind
of hopefully being able to rapidly
integrate in data from different
sources, right?
Or data lakes or data warehouses
and layering in those health checks.
Having that security built in allows
you to quickly assemble this
semantic model, which then opens
the door to immediate access
and exploration for different types
of users.
Whether it's an object explorer or
it's in Quiver, or it's in sort of a
map-based application.
And that really is sort of the
journey in a very, very
short form of kind of the first mile
of the platform, right?
Which is sort of data and
ontology.
If we now think about how digital
digital twins and modeling and data
science come into this, it gets
really exciting.
And so the first thing I'll say
here before we kind of go into the
data science part of Foundry is
if you talk to four or five data
scientists inside of Palantir and
ask them what tools they love to
use, you'll get 10 different
answers. People love to use,
you know, Foundry's built in machine
learning capabilities and authoring
capabilities, but also they love to
use data robot Dataiku,
SageMaker, Azure ML,
you name it.
And so we've tried to build this
part of the stack to set,
with the philosophy in mind, of
build anywhere and then when you're
ready to deploy into operational
applications, let's give you a
streamlined way of doing that.
And so as an example of how I might
build a model end-to-end using
Foundry's existing, kind of, data
science tooling, I'm going to open
up and kind of switch personas
again. So we talked about the data
engineering persona, some of the
business personas, now let's think
about the data science persona,
where I'm now here in an environment
that again looks kind of graph like
or sort of a
sort of lineage like, but
is intended to feel very familiar to
those who have used other data
science tooling. So if I pop
open one of the steps in my model
here and I kind of zoom out, you'll
see concepts like training sets
and feature creation, kind
of all the way back to
the objects I'm actually pulling
data from.
And so every one of these nodes is a
step of PySpark based
transformation. I could be using
Pandas.
I can be intermixing R or Spark SQL.
And you know, the joke that we have
internally is that the most
interesting thing off the bat to
data scientists is the import data
button.
It's being able to say, "hey, you
can get clean, consistent access
to that data that you've built into
the ontology or anywhere else in
Foundry." And as a data scientist,
I don't spend 80 percent of my time
rebuilding these data pipelines
myself. I can just tap into the good
work of my data ops colleagues
or my data engineering colleagues.
And if anything goes wrong with
those data pipelines like the ones
we saw before, I can get immediately
alerted to that because the health
information will flow down to me as
well.
And so I have a stable, rich,
healthy foundation to build on, and
I can then kind of use all the
packages and all the techniques that
I am familiar with here to actually
build out kind of different
models end-to-end batch
or live inference end points
and then actually plug them directly
into different operational
workflows.
And of course, I can make use of
kind of all of the packages I would
expect so we can mirror things
like can't afford you.
If you have your own package
managers, we have the added
benefit here of kind of
you can set up custom profiles that
not only have different sort of
compute profiles
associated with them, but also if
you have particularly sensitive or
license restricted libraries, you
want only certain users to be able
to use.
We can enforce that to the same
security perimeter that's enforcing
data security and ontology security
that we saw before.
So it allows people to make kind of
secure use of commercial libraries
as well.
And so the idea here is you
know, build here. We think it's a
great, streamlined set of tooling,
or you can also connect in
the same way that these tools are
connecting.
You can connect directly from the
DataRobot to Dataiku, the
SageMakers of the world to the
ontology through open APIs
or through Python clients that we
provide to all to build your models
and those environments as well.
And you can connect via REST
via JDBC via direct
file access.
We have an we have kind of a Foundry
version of Hadoop FS, and
it's super streamlined to get data
sort of in and out of Foundry and
not just data, but also lineage
information, the semantic
representations, all the versioning
information, all that's available
through the APIs.
And so the idea is you build your
models, you've built some here,
you've built some on other tools.
Now I want to be able to register
them and use them in a variety of
different end user applications.
And so what I'm going to do now is
open up my model objectives
library.
This is kind of mission control for
all the models that I've been
working with in this particular
instance of Foundry that I have
access to.
And a lot of this paradigm was
informed by some of our work in the
defense space where
there's kind of this three part sort
of approach to deploying operational
AI. There is, I first want to define
the modeling problem, right?
Not actually think about a
particular model, but what is the
objective I'm actually trying to run
with here.
I'm probably then testing dozens,
if not more models against that
objective.
And then I'm figuring out how I want
to then deploy
the winning models into production.
And so I'm going to open up a few of
the objectives we have here so we
can take a look at what's actually
going on. And
the critical thing here is this does
not mean deployed in Foundry
necessarily.
Several of these models are living
in other environments in Azure, in
AWS and through managed services
like DataRobot.
And so we're just registering these
models here, and we're going
to basically have a holistic
approach to comparing them as
we think about which ones are going
to be deployed into production.
So if I open up my customer demand
forecast, sort of objective here,
you'll see at a top level it shows
me all this kind of 360 information
about the model, right?
Hey, what are we trying to do with
this?
What's the approach kind of broadly
defined?
Some information about the latest
releases, relevant files that
actually informed or were  used to
train this particular model that
we're commonly used by every
different model that we tested,
and even lineage information about
the applications that are going to
be depending on this model.
And also, as we'll see a little bit
later on, some information that
we can about how we're actually
chaining this model with other
models inside of simulation
environments.
And it's all of that is kind of
rolled up here for me and
I can go in on the sidebar here, for
instance, take a look and say, let's
take a look at all the models that
we've actually proposed to be
kind of deployed against this
objective right now.
See, some from my colleague Matt,
some from my colleague Andrew, and I
can always look back in time to say,
OK, for like this lasso model, we
actually can see the details about
where it was built, when it was
built, and also if it was rejected,
why that was.
And so kind of the full kind of life
cycle around kind of the approval
process like we saw with data,
how we're treating data
----- like code. We're also kind of
treating models like code in kind of
the same way the metadata around the
approval process.
And, you know, if I kind of switch
over to another objective here,
which might be my sort of campaign
model, I can even go into the
comparisons tab here and take a look
and say, OK, so for different models
that we're assessing, we rejected
one of them, but let's still add it
into the comparison.
We have a random forest model and
SVM model and then your regression
model, and I want to I compare kind
of the key theories, the key
criteria across these models.
So, you know, things like the ROC
curves and how basically
the different kind of core
dimensions of evaluation
are performing across these
different models.
And so you can kind of even
customize very easily kind of what
these core dimensions are,
and you can even segment out things
that are sensitive.
So there might be, you know,
personally identifiable information
or things that have to be locked
down.
And you can actually cordon off that
kind of feature comparison or that
kind of dimensionality comparison
inside of a different set of
parts of the objective that are
only open to certain types of people
or certain folks with certain
permissions.
And so all this information is here,
and the idea is that once you've
sort of made our selection and
tagged, the model is being ready for
production.
The kind of key step here, the kind
of coronation is we're then
going to actually bind this
model to the ontology.
Now this is key because this is
basically giving us a type system
for the models.
And so what you see here at the
bottom here with the modeling
objective API is
the winning model, which in this
case was a SageMaker model
is actually going to take,
as two of its inputs, two
properties from the ontology
from from our supply chain ontology.
We've been working with this entire
time, so it's going to take the
cost.
It's going to take in the price into
this live inference end point.
And then every time it returns a
value for the endpoint, we're going
to basically take those three values
- demand, capacity, inventory -
and map those back onto the
objects in our ontology as time
dependent properties or, in this
case, model dependent properties
that could be time dependent as
well. And so the idea is that we
have configured the ontology
to basically have
to recognize to be aware of the fact
that it's going to be receiving
values from a model.
And so this is huge because what
this means is, with this binding in
place, I can now use this
model. That's sort of one,
you know, ----- it's been competed,
it's one it's now bound to the
ontology.
I can now through that ontology
binding, insert the model into not
just one application or five
applications, but dozens of
different applications and sort of
seamlessly have it appear to end
users.
And so as an example of how that
kind of comes together here in this
kind of takes us to kind of our
final mile, which is sort of
operational applications.
Let's open up a supply chain control
tower example and take a look at how
the data in the models kind of weave
together for an end user
application.
And so what we're going to open up
here is just an example of
an application that again, might be
a starting point for many users in
the enterprise.
This is sort of my top level control
tower. It's showing me some roll-up
statistics at the top, and
I see here that we've got different
objects here on a map.
As an operational user, I probably
don't care about what an ontology is
or kind of all the things that we've
been through. I just know that I
have a job to do.
So I see, you know, we have a plant
here in Michigan that need to go
take a look at actually that
production capacity is starting to
dip, and I want to know why.
Maybe I received an alert about
this, and so, you know, that alert
could have come in via email or it
could have come in via text or kind
of any sort of integration with a
messaging system.
And I can go into my alerts tab now
and take a look at kind of a
prioritized ---- set of like
kind of different alerts that I can
start to action here.
So you'll see there's all sorts of
things that are coming in here, and
maybe I just want to look at those
that are high priority.
So I'm going to filter here on the
left hand side, and I'm going to
take a look at one of these alerts
here, which is a business
interruption related to COVID.
And you'll see that this is pulling
together lots of different
information from everything we've
covered so far.
Right. This alert was generated
maybe by a model pipeline.
It is pulling in data from the
supplier, and the plants are
different links in my ontology.
It's showing me the impacted plant
that this pertains to, and it's
actually showing you recommended
actions as well, which are in this
case coming in from a model that
I've built.
The critical thing here
is we're not just stopping with
looking at this alert and saying,
"well, OK, looks like we have a
problem here." We're saying we want
to be able to take action now to
actually do something in response.
And you'll see that we have
different actions that we've
actually pre-assembled for these
users canceling an order
or partially fulfilling an order or
actually going into more advanced
actions like reallocation that will
look at in just a second.
But if I hit this cancel customer
order button, you'll see that it
allows me now to sort of it kind of
preconfigured and action I can take
here on this particular alert or a
related alert, and I can then choose
to submit this in a way that
will be nondestructively captured
back into the ontology.
And you might be asking, well, how
does this work, right?
I don't want any user to be able to
take any action on any part
of the ontology and start to update
things right. That would be chaos.
We can't have people modifying
values willy nilly.
Turns out, the way that actions work
is they're actually part of the
ontology at the core level.
So if we go back to the ontology
configuration interface that we saw
before we were talking about
bringing our plant together and all
of the connections here, if we go
back to kind of the main page, we'll
see their object types, of course,
that we're defining.
There are link types which we've
seen all throughout, but the
critical third element is actions
as well. And this is the dynamism
here that kind of makes the ontology
truly special is we're not
just talking about kind of
semantics, we're also talking about
kinetics.
We're talking about the kind of
actions that can modify the
state of the ontology in a compliant
manner.
And so if I, for instance, search
for that cancel customer order
action that we saw before, we'll see
this is in our library of actions.
And if I open this up, you'll see
all sorts of related information
like we have with other parts of the
ontology, the API
name for this, this cancel custom
order, the actual ID that we can
use, we can programmatically
interact with this and the actual
logic used to create this particular
cancel customer order action.
So we see here
what objects that pertains to, what
properties it will be updating,
what parameters it takes and even
what validations it uses as well.
And this is all kind of configured
here through point-and-click, but it
could be configured through a much
more kind of robust kind of
code-based interface as well,
using the authoring tools that we
saw before here
and kind of the more data ops part
of the stack.
And so with this action essentially
defined every time I want to cancel
a customer order, I can do so
in a reliable, repeatable, auditable
way.
And so that means that every
application builder isn't
implementing their own version of
what it means to cancel a custom
order. It means they simply use
this action of the library, and
it knows intelligently how to
basically modify different objects.
It knows what sort of precautions
to take. So if I'm a junior
employee, it might be that when
I click the cancel customer order,
it's aware of who I am and it has
to go and then get approval from my
manager before it actually
gets confirmed.
And then it might be that the last
part of this is a webhook or some
sort of write-back routine that then
actually synchronizes this change
back to an ERP or back to
an MES system.
Again, all of that is a pretty
complex flow for an action or a
piece of logic that I don't want the
application builder to have to think
about. I just want them to be able
to embed that piece of logic here as
an action and have Foundry
at a system level be able to deal
with all that orchestration that
happens thereafter.
So we've kind of alluded to this,
but what this means for the
application builder is that even
though these applications we've been
looking at here in this particular
supply chain control tower example
looks very custom - It's
actually all just built using a
low code application builder, and in
this case, a no code application
builder. And if I want to add
something here to the top, for
instance, it's very simple, just a
point-and-click my way into adding
a new widget here in
this particular view, so I could add
an object table, for instance.
And it's super simple to start to
wire in different things
into these views, right?
Because I'm not dealing with pulling
data into kind of a
kind of siloed database and trying
to do kind of things in a one-off
manner. I'm connected directly to
the ontology and so I can easily
open up a set of objects
you've been working with before,
like the plants, and I can
start to actually pull them in here
and take a look at how they will
actually get bound to these
widgets that we've set up.
And so here, I'll type in our MSC
plant in this case, and
it will now be able to pull in all
that data in a way that is aware of
who I am and my security profile.
I can add all the properties here,
and just like that, I've added in a
new widget in the same
way that I can add in data.
I can add in those actions as well.
And what this means is, as an
application developer, I no longer
have to think about the full stack
of considerations myself every time
I want to deploy a new operational
workflow or application.
I don't have to think about setting
up a new hosting environment.
The databases, the indexing, the
compute, the storage, that's maybe
non-database.
How am I capturing back feedback
from users? How am I binding models
to the different application states?
How am I capturing feedback from
those models?
All of that is taken care of below
the level of the application because
of what we saw in the data
integration, in the set up of the
ontology, and the actions in
the actual wiring in of the models
that come together in these
objectives and the actual binding
of the models to the ontology, to
these objectives as well, which
means you can do a fully feature
rich compound applications
in a couple of hours or
a day or two, as opposed to
spending months or quarters of
effort.
So we think this is a really
powerful part of the platform, and
oftentimes, you know, this is this
is just, you know, an example of
kind of where the kind of
operational capability gets
surfaced.
Kind of what we've been looking at
here is one example
of an operational application
builder called Workshop.
There are other application builders
in Foundry as well.
So there's another one called Slate
as sort of a sibling application.
And the key thing here is, of
course, you can go and you can build
your own custom applications as
well, and you can kind of do it an
object oriented manner or even do
it in a tabular manner or a more
classical manner as well.
There's kind of a full set of
documentation here around not just
sort of interacting with existing
applications, but building your
own applications, using the APIs
and Foundry using every part of what
we've talked about kind of
throughout this demo.
Awesome.
Now I have one last thing to show
you guys.
And then then we'll sign off here
for this particular demo,
and that is kind of how these things
start to come together in
kind of a more strategic kind of
digital twin paradigm.
So what am I open up here is
one final application here in
Foundry that we call Vertex.
Vertex is kind of like the map
application in Foundry.
Sorry, the graph application in
Foundry you might think of, right?
It's showing me kind of all the
relationships here, kind
of between all my different objects,
right? Like if you were just to look
at, we started here, you might think
this looks kind of nuts, right?
There's so much going on here,
but now we know exactly what this
is, right? These are this is just
showing me kind of the kind of
connection that I've built into my
ontology, right, where every one of
these object types has a lot of data
being integrated into it.
And then we've also overlaid the
different machine learning models
and data science approaches as well.
So in this case, this is an example
that's based off of
one of our medical supplier
customers, kind of loosely based
off of anonymized, of course,
from the work they did during COVID
kind of the early phases of COVID,
where they needed to really map out
kind of the full flow of how they
were building and shipping
ventilators from everything
from their upstream suppliers to
intermediate goods to their plants
all the way down to their actual
distribution centers and their end
customers themselves.
And so what this is showing here is
sort of the bird's eye view of the
entire value chain, right?
And being able to kind of scrub
backwards and forwards in time and
saying, show me where alerts are
firing, where inventory is getting
to dangerous levels, where we're
basically experiencing kind of
fundamental dislocations, right?
And I can always kind of go
backwards and forwards kind of scrub
through kind of different points in
time here to be able to look at kind
of where things were in kind of the
danger zone at different points in
time.
And so that's useful, of course, to
be able to kind of be able to get
visibility into the whole kind
of connected chain here, which was
spread across dozens of different
data systems and models before.
But the more important thing is, I
need to now be able to kind of
update my strategy and actually
operate now in this sort of very
volatile environment, which it was
last year. Right. So there were
simultaneous supply and demand
shocks and kind of every pre-built
model was kind of thrown out the
window. And so they needed to be
able to simulate kind of different
scenarios that were exigent day in
and day out.
What would happen if one of our
suppliers went completely offline
given the pandemic?
What would happen if one of our
medical center customers had 10
times normal demand they normally
have for ventilators?
How would we actually be able to
meet these different requirements,
given how we're currently doing
allocation, how we're currently
doing different supply tactics?
And so what we can open up here is
actually a simulation tab
to think about running those
simulations, those scenarios
directly on top
of sandbox versions of your
world, right, of the full ontology.
And so we can actually simulate
directly here, given that we
have the data in the models
connected,
what would happen if that supplier
went offline, for instance, and you
can kind of run these simulations as
kind of contained case studies.
And so in this case, I can make a
very trivial change, right, where I
could say, let's literally just
update the valve price per unit.
What if it dropped to four hundred?
Let's literally now simulate across
the entire chain what effects that
would have across kind of every
dependent property that we have
here, kind of modeled
in the ontology.
And so that's a very trivial
example. We can now kind of have
this sort of modified simulation
of the scenario state continuously
run as new data comes in
and we can kind of continuously
assess what its impact is.
And as you can imagine, it gets much
more complicated and sophisticated
when you're testing compound changes
to parameters across not just one
model, but potentially many
different models. So you can say I'm
not just taking one model in, but
I'm going to chain different models
together and run a compound
simulation across kind of the entire
state or the entire value chain.
And this this is, I think, where we
really see kind of the the
progression of customers working
with Foundry kind of kind of move
towards where you first were working
with point applications or
kind of starting workflows to begin
with. But really, it's about the
connected operations paradigm that
unfolds by virtue of bringing
together the ontology kind of
incrementally and, you know,
as an example, in oil and gas,
initially, they
were doing kind of point
optimizations and simulations
for one part of kind
of a connected value chain, right?
Just the subsurface.
So they had one team working on
the subsurface, integrating data,
building models and kind of just
looking at that element of what was
going on.
But of course, it's part of a
network, right? The subsurface
connects to the top side, connects
to the flow lines, connects to the
onshore.
Each of those different functions
had their own kind of siloed
simulation and optimization and data
regimes, and to really understand
how to optimize production as a
whole, for instance, they had to
connect together all of
those different parts of the
organization into one ontology,
connect together all the different
models into a single chain
representation.
And then they could actually try to
run these full-scale
continuous simulations and begin to
optimize production in that case,
a kind of a full scale.
They started to work towards really
connecting or reconnecting their
operations.
And we see this sort of again and
again, across whether it's sort of
industrials or its finance or
its retail or its health care,
you name it, that that being
kind of the North Star for us is how
are we helping our customers really
re-engineer and reintegrate their
operations.
So I know we've covered a lot today,
so I won't I won't keep keep
yammering on longer, but I just want
to make sure that we can recap here
a bit of what we've been through.
Just to leave you with this.
So, you know, we started at the top
here with how do we think about kind
of data and ontology.
So data coming together from many,
many different sources, structured,
IoT, unstructured, geospatial,
you name it, over 200 plus
out-of-the-box data connectors that
we've built for Foundry and
is extensible so you can build your
own and being able to bring
kind of all of those kind of
different pieces of data together
into a semantic representation that
allows for people to instantly start
to look, interact and kind of wield
that data.
The second piece is now how do we
bring modeling, data science,
linear programing into that same
frame so we can actually overlay
intelligence into that data and
build out not just a semantic
representation, but as we said
before, a kinetic representation?
So how does how do things actually
flow or get dictated in business
process based on what the models
dictate?
And how can you sort of build models
within Foundry, but also outside of
Foundry, and then bind those models
to the ontology?
So you can then insert those models
into operations in a way where
you're both allowing
for very robust and safe deployment
of models, but also very rich
feedback to model builders who can
know because of the data lineage,
the model lineage, kind of all the
bookkeeping that Foundry does,
exactly how users are using those
models in different applications
and also in external applications
that are using the APIs.
And then finally, we talked about
kind of how this all comes together
in again, where 70
to 80 percent of Foundry users live,
which is operational applications,
which you can build using low code,
no code or pro code application
builders and can also,
of course, be surfaced directly
via the APIs if you want to build
external applications as well.
So there's a lot more
we can cover in follow-on sessions.
You've only shown you kind of a
glimpse of kind of how all these
different tools come together and
Foundry into a cohesive platform.
We've only shown you a glimpse of
kind of all the different
interoperability
patterns that exist in Foundry.
We've only shown you a glimpse of
how you can actually kind of
deploy workflows using a workflow
catalog out-of-the-box to get
started really quickly, if you're
doing an alerting workflow or an
entity resolution workflow or a
plant-360 or resource allocation
workflow and all the pre-built
templates we have for getting
started super quickly.
But we'll save a lot of that stuff
for another time.
Thank you everybody for listening
and I hope
we can talk to you guys soon.